[SPEAKER_01]: So, we had a conversation earlier in the week, and you described how the kind of the miracle of a Sammasambuddha, in the sense that they don't have any signpost to say how far to go, in terms of discovering
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you get to this point, and then you don't go any further.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I was wondering if I could just give my interpretation of how I see that, the meaning of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: One way of describing that, in relation to, for example, paticca samapada, with this, this is...
[SPEAKER_01]: So...
[SPEAKER_01]: I have no say in the... in being in a body, or breathing, or being in a posture, or feeling, or... No, no fundamental say.
[SPEAKER_01]: Intention, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So there's...
[SPEAKER_01]: I find myself in this situation where these phenomena are present, and then...
[SPEAKER_01]: This sort of self, this sense of self, on top of these things which are not self, which are not in, which I have no say over, there is this sort of wanting pleasure and not wanting pain, and sort of, yeah, distracting from the unpleasurability of
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the point at which this sort of the middle way is, is basically seeing this responsibility for craving, yeah, that I am responsible for that, for
[SPEAKER_01]: There is still perversion.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, at the same time, yeah, there are phenomena, which are broader, or more general, that are...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's still present.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is still this experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, eh... Would it...
[SPEAKER_00]: Put it concisely, would it be kind of like coming down to seeing what you can be responsible for, and what you cannot be responsible for, and the difference between the two, which sounds like something quite simple, but it turns out not to be so easy.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're not trying to get rid of these things which you're not responsible for.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not trying to
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, you interfere with that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you are trying to discern what you are responsible for.
[SPEAKER_03]: But you are still subjective to things you're not responsible for.
[SPEAKER_03]: And the Middle Way should offer the escape from that, such as sickness, aging, death.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, how does the Middle Way offer the escape from that?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Obviously, start by recognizing responsibility.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, as long as you think the suffering is caused by things in the world or objects of your attention and so on, you won't see where the problem is.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, taking responsibility, then you might get to understand that the craving is the root of suffering.
[SPEAKER_03]: But how then, what to do in terms of...
[SPEAKER_03]: So, in terms of that middle way practice, that would then free you even from things you are not responsible for, but you are subjected to and burdened by.
[SPEAKER_03]: Anyone?
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean... Well, I would say that it is
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's not as simple as saying, you know, there's things that you're totally not responsible for, which you're subjected to.
[SPEAKER_00]: The reason that the Middle Way frees you even from those, is that you are kind of indirectly responsible for, I suppose, maintaining or, eh...
[SPEAKER_03]: So, if that's how we define it now, then, is there anything that you're completely not responsible for, because that's how we started, that would be relevant somehow?
[SPEAKER_01]: I would say no.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because, as he said, you need to recognize what you are responsible for.
[SPEAKER_03]: No, I was just saying, because I think, the way you were describing it, it's kind of things you're not responsible for meant things that you're indirectly responsible for.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: But since we more accurately define it now, I think we have to say that then things you're not responsible for, you're not responsible for, and they wouldn't be burdening you.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, yeah, sickness, aging and death, if that's how we call it now, is something you are indirectly responsible for, if it bothers you, if you're subjected to.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, how then... what would be the way out of that?
[SPEAKER_00]: I actually had a
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, a kind of a... there was this... even to put it as a simile that occurred to me in regard to that.
[SPEAKER_00]: How it's... how it seems is that... if you think of like... it's like a burning fire that is... that is burning you with this heat.
[SPEAKER_00]: The common sense automatic reaction is to...
[SPEAKER_00]: I need to burn... sorry...
[SPEAKER_00]: The reaction to it automatically or immediately with common sense with everybody is, I need to put out this burning fire.
[SPEAKER_00]: I need to put something on it, put water on it, do something to put it out.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: What you realize with the Middle Way is that, actually,
[SPEAKER_00]: It's everything I put on this fire is actually adding to the fire.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the reason that I'm burned by this burning fire, that it's there in the first place, is as a result of me over all of the past... all I've been doing all my life, is adding to the fire, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: Basically fueling it inadvertently.
[SPEAKER_00]: Inadvertently.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, all I have to do is actually not
[SPEAKER_00]: I have to keep fueling this fire.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, not only will I know that all I have to do is not keep fueling the fire, and it will have to go out eventually, but even then, because I don't go to the fire to put something on it and try to put it out, I realize that actually
[SPEAKER_00]: Already, that is directly removing a huge weight of suffering, because when you go to the fire, you get burnt, to put something on it, to get out.
[SPEAKER_00]: But when you don't go to it, you don't get burnt.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you would see the results here and now, in that way.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you hear the results here and now, and then...
[SPEAKER_03]: The trick, obviously, now, is to... or rather, the next step would be then to define what would constitute not fueling the fire, because people can...
[SPEAKER_03]: Practice not fueling of the fire, that's still actively fueling it.
[SPEAKER_03]: In other words, when they say, I'm not fueling the fire, they're doing it in a way that it's actually fueling the fire.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that's why it's not just a question of simply putting stuff and abstaining from everything that will make the fire go away.
[SPEAKER_03]: You know, you've got to find that middle way, because abstaining from... if you abstain from too much, if you denounce too much, too many things in a way that just doesn't still see where the line of responsibility is, that's another way of fueling the fire.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that's the whole kind of the two ways of indulgent, you know, sensuality, blaming the world, trying to get rid of it, so on.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then the other one denying and trying to, sort of, like, you know, cancel everything, internally and externally.
[SPEAKER_03]: Both would be equally burning.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, then, the middle way would come, obviously, as we say, gradual training, as I should say.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, again, more specifically, how that non-fueling of the fire culminates, that you know now you cannot be burned,
[SPEAKER_03]: Finished.
[SPEAKER_03]: Not just in this life, but done.
[SPEAKER_03]: What would be the measure of that success?
[SPEAKER_03]: We said it last time.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, I was thinking that it's probably the most obvious way to say it would be with the anatta, that there is complete nāma.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because it is, that is, you know.
[SPEAKER_03]: And obviously, there's a right way of going about it and that's what we keep talking about, you know, trying to get rid of things, you know, blaming things, you know, trying to sort of...
[SPEAKER_03]: Mechanically, just do certain practices and then hope that these experiences will come on their own.
[SPEAKER_03]: They need to be understood on the basis of what you already are.
[SPEAKER_03]: But nevertheless, yeah, that should be the goal.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it's not just about enduring and putting up and not acting out and so on.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's about that as a basis, but then... so that then the insight, correct insight of true anatta can be established, can be discerned,
[SPEAKER_03]: Recognized, and then cultivated, and brought to fulfillment.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you know, like we mentioned before, in the previous talk, paticampāda, and so on, and it does boil down to that simultaneous principle.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, if you read the suttas, you see, it's kind of quite often described in many different ways, as you mentioned last time, I think, or the time before.
[SPEAKER_03]: You know, whether it's like the food for the thing that is present, that depends on food,
[SPEAKER_03]: would exemplify the simultaneous relationship or, like, you know, with the present condition.
[SPEAKER_03]: This is the present result.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, the point is to understand that it's not on the level of cause and effect, but on, like, things that depend one on the other.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, as you said, when you started... when you opened this up, you kind of... you said, oh, this is the, like, the sense of self and so on, and then things that are not, kind of, in your control, that are, kind of, the...
[SPEAKER_03]: Inescapable limits of your situation.
[SPEAKER_03]: Those are the basis.
[SPEAKER_03]: You can't go outside of those.
[SPEAKER_03]: You can't go outside of the body, the posture, the perceptions, and so on.
[SPEAKER_03]: So then, that whole sense of self, it's not enough to just say, oh, this is not mine, not I am, not myself.
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean, if you're a noble disciple, that's, yeah, you need to do.
[SPEAKER_03]: Not just say it, but keep applying that attitude.
[SPEAKER_03]: to that phenomenon of self.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's what we'll encourage monks to do.
[SPEAKER_03]: But in order to do that, first you need to see that sense of self, and then you need to see that sense of self as not yours, not being independent on a master existing outside of the... that inescapability of your situation.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it's really not so much about
[SPEAKER_03]: Finding an answer to the question of myself and not-self and so on, it's really about the mental practice of whatever that sense of self is, whichever way it endures, to see it as second, as within, as fully enclosed, within this inescapable limits of this situation, you know, body posture, your current enduring feeling and so on.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then it's the same.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, what's next?
[SPEAKER_03]: No, that's it.
[SPEAKER_03]: You will fall from it, you know.
[SPEAKER_03]: And obviously, you won't even do it rightly the first time.
[SPEAKER_03]: But if you know that it's supposed to...
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you're not supposed to remove the sense of self.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're simply supposed to set it up through your attention and yoniso, that attention, as impossible to own while it is still there.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, the sense of self
[SPEAKER_03]: And you can all, like, recall your sense of self now, as we speak.
[SPEAKER_03]: It has to be there.
[SPEAKER_03]: It doesn't matter whether it's exemplified through a clear thought or ambiguous.
[SPEAKER_03]: The sense of I am, sitting here, that I am, it's obviously not this physical thing.
[SPEAKER_03]: But it's that gratuitous separation that's been maintained through desire, greed, aversion, delusion, and so on.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, the question is not to, like, as I said, remove or ignore the sense of self, but not to kind of try to force it either into, oh, it's not self, it's not self, it's like this, it's like the floor, it's like these branches, it's the sweet dimension.
[SPEAKER_03]: No.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you want to say there's a sense of self-enduring, and there is a situation of disbodied perception, sounds, smells, tastes, touches, enduring.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, if that's too complex, you could simply say, oh, well, okay, there is there is this situation on the basis of this body, for whatever it is, to whatever extent it is, and there is this sense of self.
[SPEAKER_03]: Do you see that?
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, forget about, okay, so this going first, this is within the other, this is not mine, just that can come into play later.
[SPEAKER_03]: But for now, do you see your sense of self enduring simultaneously on a different plane from
[SPEAKER_03]: Your five senses, and your thoughts, and everything else.
[SPEAKER_03]: So...
[SPEAKER_03]: So, here and yonder, as my situation of this, you know, infinite space, so to speak, and my sense of self, kind of perpendicular to that, simultaneously here.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because in any given time, it doesn't matter what you would engage with, if somebody were to ask you, who are you, or something, you would have that there.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, but the point is to not bother, or not spend too much time trying to define who you are, or who this I am is, or what is.
[SPEAKER_03]: Just seeing enduring.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're seeing it enduring there, as this weird, ambiguous concept, phenomenon, that can never be kind... you can never put your finger on it, but it's always there.
[SPEAKER_03]: The point is to not even bother trying to put a finger on it, but to not lose the sight of it as something that is always there.
[SPEAKER_03]: See, as much as the...
[SPEAKER_03]: Your body, your current posture, your feeling, your perception, is the kind of, as we said, the basis of that inescapability of this situation here and yonder.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, the image of the self, or the notion of the self, is equally the other end of your inescapability of your situation.
[SPEAKER_03]: You are not outside of that image either.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, when you recognize that these two things
[SPEAKER_03]: They don't even know about you.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, your body, your situation is there on its own, and then you realize, oh, this phenomenon is there on its own, pretty much as a result of this here, that it's on its own.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, of course, sense of self being more ambiguous, more kind of in the background, less palpable, less measurable,
[SPEAKER_03]: Always naturally, it kind of gets bundled with that aroma of subjectivity and mine and I am, because it's kind of, you know, always... it's always above all of this, it's always outside all of this, it's always the observer of all of this.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, it doesn't matter what kind of observer it is and how it might feel.
[SPEAKER_03]: The only reason it can be an observer is because there is this to be observed.
[SPEAKER_03]: If there is nothing to be observed, the observer will not be self-aware of... there's nothing defining it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it's to recognize that it's not the observer comes first, and this comes second, or this comes first... No, it's with the observer, this is, the observed is.
[SPEAKER_03]: With the observed, felt, perceived, tasted, touched, the observer is.
[SPEAKER_03]: So,
[SPEAKER_03]: Without...
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean, you know, if your mind is calm within this principle, and you have room to move without sort of falling off from it, so to speak, from this type of samādhi, sure, you can then think about various particular aspects of this relationship.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, fundamentally, the point is simply to get very used to having a sense of self endure, simultaneously with having this experience endure as it changes, and you speak, and you move, and you stand up, and so on.
[SPEAKER_03]: Two simultaneous things at the same time.
[SPEAKER_03]: And, as we said before, if that becomes something you just see normally, because you've been looking for it, that self-centered one point of view, at the same time, will be undermined, simply through that.
[SPEAKER_03]: And, as I was saying to you, maybe to you, before, the other day, that's how people practiced on account of faith, sādhā, in the Buddha.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, they had minimal instruction,
[SPEAKER_03]: And it's sometimes puzzling.
[SPEAKER_03]: You read the suttas and somebody just had faith and became an arahant as a result of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: People will think, oh, they had faith on the level of the guru is the greatest and I'm so devotional, so the enlightenment will happen to me because, you know, I'm I'm such a good follower.
[SPEAKER_03]: But no, actually, this is what it means.
[SPEAKER_03]: It means they understood this basic principle.
[SPEAKER_03]: They haven't understood any single implication afterwards.
[SPEAKER_03]: They didn't need to.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, they stuck to the very basic recognition of what this, this is, which is...
[SPEAKER_02]: There was no Pārthaṭṭhīja-saṃbhapāda, you know, the person didn't... Yeah, yeah, sure, exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: Read the whole thing.
[SPEAKER_03]: He didn't, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: He just, as there were cases, says, ah, Master Gautama explains the condition, conditions of everything that has arisen.
[SPEAKER_03]: Now, you can translate that in a manner of cause and effect, but you can also understand that, the hetu, the condition, the basis, means like, okay, so,
[SPEAKER_03]: Master Gautama understands or teaches the undermining of the sense of self.
[SPEAKER_03]: The undermining of one through having two simultaneously present.
[SPEAKER_03]: And somebody understands that and sees it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, not just, oh, that's a lovely idea.
[SPEAKER_03]: I have faith in it.
[SPEAKER_03]: No, I say, oh, this sense of self and this.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, what if I stick to this and contemplate it?
[SPEAKER_03]: Out of faith in Master Gautama, they were so inspiring to see, they actually did it.
[SPEAKER_03]: And as a result of it, even without bothering with
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, making effort towards kind of more specific clarifications and permutations, they... they arrived at the final goal of dispassion, because that is what's... although it's needed.
[SPEAKER_03]: With this, this is.
[SPEAKER_03]: Without this, this would not be.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thus, anything else that you assume is in between, it will just evaporate.
[SPEAKER_03]: Especially, anything else that you assume is mine and the...
[SPEAKER_03]: Pertaining to the core of that subjectivity, that will just vanish.
[SPEAKER_03]: It will just sort of dissipate.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's one of those other contemplations, like recognizing that this body, i.e.
[SPEAKER_03]: this situation of mine, that I'm enclosed with, and so on, oh, it's dependent.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's sitting upon food, having food.
[SPEAKER_03]: Having to eat these external things, as a whole, just the phenomenon of food, is why this body is alive.
[SPEAKER_03]: No other reason.
[SPEAKER_03]: You take that away,
[SPEAKER_03]: The body will not be able to remain alive.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, like, the atmosphere and breathing, like, the oxygen and... Well, the element of air, sure.
[SPEAKER_03]: There are four great elements.
[SPEAKER_03]: They're in a particular arrangement that your body is made of.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you just need to add a bit more of one, remove a bit more of the other, and that's it.
[SPEAKER_03]: You won't be anymore.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's all it takes.
[SPEAKER_03]: And there was that reflection of
[SPEAKER_03]: Recollecting, you know, the great earth and the mountain, you know, that they would crumble and get destroyed and broken.
[SPEAKER_03]: What is then to be said for this sort of little tiny ant that lives on top of it?
[SPEAKER_03]: It's just inconceivable to remember.
[SPEAKER_03]: But again, it's not... You can think of it in that linear way of, oh, this will be destroyed, thus I will be destroyed.
[SPEAKER_03]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_03]: You see the earth as this.
[SPEAKER_03]: And you see your body as this is, as a result of that earth, simultaneously present.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, if that earth, that is simultaneously the necessary condition for your entire existence, changes, that's it.
[SPEAKER_03]: You don't need to know what will happen to the... or rather witness what will happen to what this is, to my body.
[SPEAKER_03]: You will immediately feel it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, and that what you feel is what anatta is.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, if you cultivate that, on the basis of precepts, sense restraint and solitude, because otherwise, you're just going to be dwelling with anxiety in and out, and not... and trying to get rid of it as well, with yourself.
[SPEAKER_03]: But if you have been cultivating the gradual training beforehand, this will actually be liberating.
[SPEAKER_03]: That undermining the sense of self, in that directly simultaneous manner, will feel like a relief from the burden, from the tension, from the presence.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's why the Noble Eightfold Path is the way for that to become your experience established.
[SPEAKER_03]: Not just, you know, this, this, this technique.
[SPEAKER_03]: No, it's not entirely.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, your actions, your intentions, your livelihood, all of that built up is contributing towards sustaining this up until it cannot be otherwise.
[SPEAKER_03]: The non-self.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, would it be correct to say that it's important to, for example, if you want to contemplate the element of earth in regard to the body, to do that while seeing
[SPEAKER_00]: The body as where your sense of self is, if you know what I mean like that, the... you don't take it as something separate from your sense of self.
[SPEAKER_00]: I would...
[SPEAKER_03]: I would think it depends.
[SPEAKER_03]: I guess, yeah, it could work.
[SPEAKER_03]: But I think what can also result in, it's basically mixing like the two different approaches.
[SPEAKER_03]: Although they will individually arrive at the same, either take your sense of self and undermine it with the present situation, or with the earth, or whatever, or even if you take this body in its extent, like this situation, this body, and that earth, that in between will be where your sense of self is.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, if you set it up correctly, it cannot remain unaffected, in other words.
[SPEAKER_03]: But yes, sometimes this will feel clearer, sometimes something else will feel clearer.
[SPEAKER_03]: But the point is to keep trying to pretty much revoke and maintain that same direct principle inside of... that undermines itself.
[SPEAKER_03]: That doesn't require the owner, the master, the center, your center-self to be there, witnessing, observing, experiencing, and so on.
[SPEAKER_03]: No, it's kind of stretched in between the two.
[SPEAKER_03]: And you realize, well, if either of these changes...
[SPEAKER_03]: My sense of self cannot remain.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thus, it's not mine.
[SPEAKER_03]: How can it be mine?
[SPEAKER_03]: Or, this sense of self is the master controller of this great experience, except that it's neither the master nor in control of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it's a star system.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, what is it then?
[SPEAKER_03]: It doesn't matter what it is.
[SPEAKER_03]: What matters is that you keep confusing it as your subject, as your ownership, and so on.
[SPEAKER_03]: Remove that, then you'll see what it is.
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean, I can give an answer, but then people say, okay, that's what the self is.
[SPEAKER_03]: But that's not the point.
[SPEAKER_03]: The point is not to find an answer to what self or not-self is.
[SPEAKER_03]: The point is to remove that ownership through setting up correctly that necessary basis for its presence that cannot be your sense of self at the same time.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yet, your sense of self fully sits upon it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Say, that's satipaṭṭhāna, like body in the body.
[SPEAKER_03]: Means, again, same.
[SPEAKER_03]: This within this.
[SPEAKER_03]: Feeling within the feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mind within mind.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's when you need to have the right view for that as well.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, yes, if you want to contemplate the element of earth, you could, either, if you accurately, on some days, you'll be more accurate than on others, but, yeah, recollect the element of earth, then see there's a necessary basis to this body, until you get that kind of, you know, sort of converging point on your feeling, so to speak, where it's kind of neither here nor there.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then you might be... your mind might push you to provide more clarity, more answers for these... for this phenomenon, but that's like, oh, now you're overtightening the strings.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you just learn to see these two things, and then restrain or refrain from all the, okay, but I need to see nāmarūpa and viññāṇa, and viññāṇa and nāmarūpa, and this and that.
[SPEAKER_03]: And so, yeah, okay, well, if I see this sufficiently enough, those things will be recognized there on their own, because that's where they are.
[SPEAKER_03]: Sometimes, you might not be able to recollect the element of earth accurately, so you start with your body situation, and then discern the element of earth through this body, not as something left, right, before or after.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because, while this body is seated here, the factual element of earth, the solidity, pertains to it, while this body is seated here.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's, I mean, that's exactly how the body is defined for you, through the degree that it resists you, to the degree that it's solid independently.
[SPEAKER_03]: And there you go.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's already enough of a degree for non-ownership of your situation.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, what I do now?
[SPEAKER_03]: Eh, exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: Tune that further and let it play.
[SPEAKER_03]: For as long as it endures.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when it stops enduring, when it disappears, then set it up again.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when you say when it stops enduring... Means when you get distracted, your mind goes away.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, I guess one way of describing that, it could be that you sort of get... you move back into more particular experiences.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, you fell off from the balance.
[SPEAKER_01]: The general, yeah, this bigger picture.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, you either moved into, like, too general,
[SPEAKER_03]: Absurd, like mystical.
[SPEAKER_03]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: Not necessarily mystical, because mysticism is on the level of the views, but more like abstract, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like you're now thinking earth and stuff, but not on the basis of the resonant, enduring body.
[SPEAKER_03]: Or you just fall onto the, you know, here and yonder, where the senses are, and sense objects, and then just get absorbed into that.
[SPEAKER_03]: Or even like, you see, you cease to approach your body as a recognition of your whole situation, but you kind of end up approaching it as particular sensations or parts of the body and so on, that you're kind of
[SPEAKER_03]: Attending to.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's again falling onto the level of the sense objects.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're not the same.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, the body as a whole.
[SPEAKER_03]: The body as a basis for this entire situation, which it is there.
[SPEAKER_03]: The body posture.
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean, how can you specifically observe your body posture?
[SPEAKER_03]: The only reason you can observe specific parts of your body posture is because you already know what posture you're in.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it's quite the opposite from, like, the body sweeping.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's actually recognizing the... the... the... as I said, recollect the memory of your posture, the image, the thought that is there.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that is factually here.
[SPEAKER_01]: Preceding yourself in this case.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sorry?
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm...
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, yeah, I always find...
[SPEAKER_01]: I add to... when you say this, I always add, like, that discernment will then be uprooting the sense of self somehow.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because...
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not, you're not reflecting on the problem.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, so, because, as I said, the more, the clearer it becomes, this, this is, the two simultaneous things,
[SPEAKER_03]: Even if you don't specifically think about the ownership and this and uprooting it, it is being uprooted.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because it prevents you from owning.
[SPEAKER_03]: The assumption of one experience center, self-owner.
[SPEAKER_03]: Sometimes people mystify it and say, oh, it's the observer, the pure consciousness, the knower, the this, the that.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's just basically different phrasing for the same thing.
[SPEAKER_03]: I am.
[SPEAKER_03]: But that's not the way up.
[SPEAKER_02]: Never has been.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you want to see that it doesn't matter how lofty, how remote, how distant, how great that observer of the knower might feel.
[SPEAKER_03]: Would he be there if this situation is not enduring the way it is out of your hands, pretty much?
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thus, with this, this is.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that all-knowing seer, knower, it's pretty much
[SPEAKER_03]: To the same extent, not a bit more, not a bit less, subjected to exactly the same things that all of this is subjected to.
[SPEAKER_03]: Impermanence, dukkha and unability.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, then, it doesn't matter how it feels.
[SPEAKER_03]: What matters is that it ceases to be yours.
[SPEAKER_03]: Either way.
[SPEAKER_03]: Whether it feels coarse or lofty, that's in itself.
[SPEAKER_03]: Coarse or lofty, refined, whatever.
[SPEAKER_03]: Pleasant or unpleasant, it's just a reflection of the same principle that's here.
[SPEAKER_03]: Nothing else.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, that's the true unburdening, basically.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because there is now no more of that assumed center that takes all the weight on.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a bit like, like you said, one of the other times, the more one sort of gets used to this type of contemplation, the less it will be dissonant,
[SPEAKER_00]: In regards to the sense of security and the sense of self, if you know what I mean, like that it's... it's like, you know, if something you thought was so solid and so secure, the first time you realize that actually it's just this flimsy house of cards, it's like a... Terrifying.
[SPEAKER_00]: Terrifying.
[SPEAKER_00]: But now, you know, if it's just a house of cards, it's a house of cards.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't expect it to be anything else.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: If you, if you, through, again, through gradual training, sense of change, you actually stop fueling
[SPEAKER_03]: Stop adding more fuel to the fire of passion, aversion and ownership.
[SPEAKER_03]: Then, yeah, the more of the same recognition that this house of cards is flimsy and is going to collapse, the more you have it, the less unpleasant it will be.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it was unpleasant not because of the recognition, but because of your emotional involvement with the house of cards, dependence on it, views, refusal to allow it to be otherwise, out of that, again, gratuitous sense of ownership of the, you know, like the self-centered experience.
[SPEAKER_03]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_03]: But I want it like this.
[SPEAKER_03]: The question is that even when the doubt cannot prevail the principle anymore, because it's part of it, it's within it.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's how you go beyond doubt, by not having ability to doubt.
[SPEAKER_03]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: The doubt doesn't hinder the basic insight anymore.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's very bad to think that doubt is a sort of bad quality or
[SPEAKER_00]: It's unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, people naturally then, like, oh, I must, you know, I just can't bear this anymore.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it is a hindrance and from that point of view, it is a bad quality because it does require kind of inadvertently stepping back into that self-centered point of view.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's only when the doubt is possible.
[SPEAKER_03]: But if despite the doubt, in face of a doubting mind, you still see this, this is,
[SPEAKER_03]: That, because it is such a fundamental principle, that if you develop it sufficiently enough, yeah, doubt is obviously second to it.
[SPEAKER_03]: And you, even now, you can see how doubt would be second to it.
[SPEAKER_03]: But the point is to keep having doubt included within the principle when doubt is there.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, the question is not to how not to doubt.
[SPEAKER_03]: The question is how to then surmount the doubt with the same principle of non-ownership.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, yeah, it just becomes impossible for doubt to access that which precedes it, which is a necessary basis.
[SPEAKER_03]: Then, you might doubt other things, and then the doubt as a hindrance will still persist, in regard to this or that, in regard to pressuring the mind, trying to get you to act, to clarify, to fuel the craving further.
[SPEAKER_03]: But it can never spill outside.
[SPEAKER_03]: In the same sense, the conceit that's left, the sense of I am that's left, the degree of passion, aversion that's left, cannot spill outside into that...
[SPEAKER_03]: Previously assumed attavāda and the the sense of self independent of these aggregates and this experience and everything else, the absolute master control that's outside of all of this, that's inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_03]: You can have those thoughts as an empty phrases pretty much, but all you see is this, this, and that becomes meaningless thoughts, like shells of your previous beliefs.
[SPEAKER_03]: And the only reason they were there is because you didn't know.
[SPEAKER_03]: It was impossible.
[SPEAKER_03]: You thought it was possible.
[SPEAKER_03]: You assumed possibility of being outside of this experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_03]: Assuming the possibility of being outside of the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_03]: But when all you have is this body within this body, mind within the mind, or body within the earth, earth within the body, whichever way,
[SPEAKER_03]: If when you have that simultaneous dependence that doesn't require you, that has no room for you, then there is no outside of that.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's good news.
[SPEAKER_03]: Initially, same as you just said in terms of the house of God, having no outside will be scary, because you assume that's where the freedom is, but it's not.
[SPEAKER_03]: If there were outside, that would be just another thing you're subjected to.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, even worse thing we are subjected to.
[SPEAKER_03]: Even bigger thing we are subjected to.
[SPEAKER_03]: But all we are subjected to is this and this.
[SPEAKER_03]: This, this is.
[SPEAKER_03]: Which is all.
[SPEAKER_03]: Which is the entire saṃsāra, if left unchecked and ignored.
[SPEAKER_03]: But no, sometimes people can also think like...
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay, maybe they don't take it on that level, but they think, oh, if I have the right view,
[SPEAKER_03]: This doubt would not exist.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, doubting mind would not be able to be there.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, this is the other discussion.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's actually the opposite, basically.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: But it's like, no, no, no, you still are going to have a doubt.
[SPEAKER_03]: But the facts are no longer for the sort of... Well, exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's the other discussion we had a few weeks ago.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, so, you know, it's just that the... How far can that doubt pervert the order?
[SPEAKER_03]: That will not be... That, that will be reined in.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because, again, your situation remains
[SPEAKER_03]: You can have any hindrance.
[SPEAKER_03]: With this, this is.
[SPEAKER_03]: With this, sensuality is.
[SPEAKER_03]: With this, ill-will is.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you can't doubt that principle.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, yeah, you can say that, but you can still doubt whatever your doubt turns into.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's just to recognize that while you're doubting it, there is a simultaneously enduring basis that's a necessary basis for that doubt.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that doubt is not yours.
[SPEAKER_03]: There is no outside of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, so, because doubt is always about something.
[SPEAKER_02]: There's something that you're doubting.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: You cannot just have the phenomena of doubt sitting there in the vacuum.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, even from that point of view, it's intentional.
[SPEAKER_02]: And as such, there has to be something that's doubted.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, unnecessary based on you.
[SPEAKER_03]: But it's just that you put that craving and pressure of doubt first, and that which is doubted second.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, it's endless.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you can doubt the principle.
[SPEAKER_03]: You can.
[SPEAKER_03]: You can take it as an object and start doubting it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: But that, of course, doesn't mean that, like, when you start doubting it, when you took it as an object, it ceases, basically, to be seen as the actual principle.
[SPEAKER_02]: But then somebody who has the right view would know that that is not in accordance with the right view, I presume.
[SPEAKER_02]: What?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, what you just said.
[SPEAKER_02]: That the principle is just an idea.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes, but there's a difference between thinking about a principle
[SPEAKER_03]: Strapulating it in an idea, which is very much something you can doubt, that's what the Buddha asked the monks.
[SPEAKER_03]: Monks, the one who is not clear about this, that endures here and now, is he doubtful?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: The one who is clear, can he be doubtful?
[SPEAKER_03]: No.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's the point.
[SPEAKER_03]: But yes, if you lose the clarity of this, this, on a present basis, and start thinking about it in terms of abstract thoughts, then, yeah, that's that's
[SPEAKER_03]: It's the the ingredients of the principle.
[SPEAKER_03]: The principle is only when your situation is the basis of it, when it's included, when it's felt, when it's there.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so that's a kind of a limit to how far then you could continue.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, yeah, if you have understood that principle and developed it to the extent necessary whereby you realize, oh, you know, my mind can turn to it, but it's ridiculous because I see that doubt within the principle.
[SPEAKER_03]: Nothing can change.
[SPEAKER_03]: Then, yeah, the mind will stop trying to doubt it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, so that needs to be seen once only, I presume.
[SPEAKER_03]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_03]: Same, same.
[SPEAKER_03]: There's going to be like polishing of the of the of the dirty brass pot.
[SPEAKER_03]: And yeah, each time it's going to be cleaner, but only next time you'll see they can be even cleaner.
[SPEAKER_01]: You described it, um, this week we were talking about as like a stretch every every time.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, yeah, yeah, like, like, if your mind sort of
[SPEAKER_03]: falls onto the the senses or goes into the abstractions.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, it's almost like a like a mental stretch to hold on.
[SPEAKER_03]: This situation is a whole, this body, element of earth within it, or whatever, this sense of self, on the base of this present enduring situation of the senses.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, two simultaneous things.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then you fall from it, sometimes just too doubtful to begin with.
[SPEAKER_03]: That means maybe you're trying too forcefully to to set it up.
[SPEAKER_03]: The point is to discern the principle on account of what's already enduring.
[SPEAKER_03]: Not do it on account of, okay, now I shall see this, because that's always going to give rise to craving.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that's how we learn to think without craving as well, to intend without craving.
[SPEAKER_03]: You intend on the basis of what's already there, semi-intended, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, to start with the situation as a whole, and within that, discern rightly, rather than starting with...
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you start with situation as a whole, i.e.
[SPEAKER_03]: with what you're attending, but within that, you don't attend the next thing, you discern
[SPEAKER_03]: The origin of that attention that's simultaneously present.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, manasikāra and the yonis of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, with this, this is.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's what that means.